have heard about on social media
on Tuesday that relates to
something we talked about in
class on Tuesday.
Does anyone know what I'm
talking about?
I went home after class, and I
saw this on Twitter.
And I was like, this is exactly
the kind of thing we were
talking about, and it was
everywhere.
Does anyone know?
It's the Dyson AI toothbrush.
How many people heard about
this?
If you read the,
like, so Dyson just released
this new $500 toothbrush that
has a camera built in that'll,
like,
when you're using it, it'll, I
don't know, use the camera to
figure out where there's like
plaque and gaps in your teeth,
and it'll like automatically
spray water at those gaps.
But if you read the press
release that they had about it,
it says they use a machine
learning system trained on
470,000 dental images,
which means all they did was
supervised learning of what
places to target when brushing
people's teeth.
So this is just more evidence
that this is the kind of thing
That is actually used in
practice
Is this a useful use of it, I
don't know who knows maybe in
ten years we're all using AI
toothbrushes
anyways
Announcements so first thanks
for coming to lab yesterday the
solutions for lab one are posted
The same place everything else
for our course is posted which
is on the course home page while
we're here You'll see for
lecture one the stuff.
I wrote on my iPad is posted
here if you click in class notes
and the recording button is
right here so you can you don't
have to look anywhere else for
that stuff.
For lab one everything you need
is here,
the problems are here,
and the way I have this site set
up is that you can like look at
the solution for just one
question at a time and this is
useful for if you are coming
back to lab assignments and like
sort of want to practice them
when getting ready for exams and
you want to like look at the
solution for one thing but not
have to look at the solutions
for everything else to get
there.
This allows you to toggle
individual solutions.
But if you'd rather look at them
in their PDF views, everything
will be offered that way as
well.
And then, as I mentioned,
homework one is also out.
And it's not due until next
Friday.
But you should review the
solutions to lab one before
working or while working on
homework one.
One thing that often surprises
students in this class is that
reviewing and having a solid
grasp of the lab assignments is
just as important as for the
homework assignments because lab
assignments are where we put the
like first foundational
questions that give you like a
high level understanding of the
material and then homework
questions will go a little
deeper so it'll often be hard to
make everything on homework make
sense without having a good
understanding of the lab.
Okay
what else?
Along with the first homework
there's the welcome survey due
next Friday.
Ideally try and fill out the
welcome survey sooner so that I
I can reach out to students with
accommodations and then start to
plan alternate exams.
And then lastly, office hours,
if you go to the calendar tab of
the course website, you can see
them there.
I have office hours usually
after lecture every Tuesday and
Thursday, including today.
And then we have several other
office hours.
And we will try and open a few
select Zoom office hours as well
on other days.
The plan for today is to start
by recapping a few of the high
level ideas we finished
Tuesday's class with.
We introduced a few new words,
hypothesis functions,
parameters,
we're going to talk about what
those are again,
and then we are going to push
further,
ultimately with the goal of
trying to figure out how to make
the most accurate and best
predictions.
Sound okay?
All right,
scroll past this AI toothbrush.
Towards the end of Tuesday's
class,
this was one of the graphs that
we looked at quite a bit.
It was a scatterplot on which
the x-axis represented the time
we left to go to work in the
morning, and the y-axis
represented how long it took to
get to work.
So each one of these data
points,
or each one of the points on
this scatterplot reflects one
row of some real person's log
that they took every day,
that they wrote down every day
they went to work.
And our goal was to try and
build the model that would allow
us to predict commute times in
the future.
And what that model would do is
that it would allow me to plug
in the time I want to leave in
the morning.
And it would give me its
prediction for how long it
thinks it'll take for me to get
to school if I leave at that
time.
And that model will be trained
and will learn a pattern from
this historical data that we've
already collected.
But ultimately, our eventual
goal is for the model to work
well on future data when we
don't exactly know what the
commute times are going to look
like.
Here's one thing I should have
emphasized on Tuesday that I
didn't.
There's an assumption about the
world we need to make in order
for this process to yield
something useful.
That is,
we're using this historical
data.
What must be true about the
future in order for the model
that we make using this
historical data to still be
useful?
Gavin.
The future has to be similar to
the past? Yeah,
future commute patterns need to
look similar to past commute
patterns.
But if they open a brand new
Autobahn-type highway with no
traffic on it, maybe all of
these commute times will go
down.
Or if they close all of the
highways,
or who knows?
If any aspect of the system in
which this data was collected
changes,
the data that we used from the
past may not represent data in
the future.
And so the models we learn on it
may not be representative.
Does that sound reasonable?
OK.
And this is why, putting this in
context of things like ChatGPT,
I actually got a survey from
some linguistics researcher at
another university who asked
questions about this,
about how
there are lots of different
dialects of English.
And many of us in this room, or
at least at the university, we
speak American English.
But there's British English,
Canadian English.
And different parts of the world
have their own dialects of
English.
But because the creators of the
large language models primarily
think in American English,
and so the models are trained
and fine-tuned to speak that
sort of dialect,
then people in other parts of
the world who have their own
versions of English that don't
sound like the way that our
English sounds,
or the way that English sounds
here in Michigan,
are sort of biased towards our
way of speaking English, even if
it's not necessarily right, it's
just our way.
So, like,
for example, you could imagine
someone being in a country where
English isn't the first
language, but it's a popular
second language, and you may put
in, like, an essay that you
wrote and say,
I don't know, fix the grammar
here.
You could imagine it fixing a
lot of things that aren't
actually issues, they're just
not as American as they could
be.
And why is that happening?
It's because the training data
doesn't reflect the reality in
which the model is trying to be
used.
So this is a problem even for
large systems that you work with
every day.
So our goal here is to try and
predict commute times as best as
we could.
And to do that,
I introduced the term hypothesis
function.
Can someone remind me what a
hypothesis function is and what
symbol I referred to them by on
Tuesday.
What is a hypothesis function?
Yes, and remind me of your name.
Actually, tell me the first
letter of it, and I'll try and
guess it.
A.
I'm sorry, I don't remember.
Allison.
Yes.
OK.
You said that a hypothesis
function is represented with H,
and it takes in features, and it
returns the predicted y's.
Good.
A hypothesis function is the
function we use to make our
predictions.
So it takes in features, which
are our input variables as an
input, and what it returns is a
predicted y value.
So here,
xi is an input called a feature
outputs is
a predicted
yi value,
OK?
And there were two formats of
hypothesis functions, or two
types of hypothesis functions,
that we proposed on Tuesday.
What were the two?
Yes, and remind me of your name?
Maj.
Near and constant.
Good, the first one,
and the one that we will spend
all of our time on today
was the constant model.
So let me bring this to the next
page.
The constant model,
the formula looks a little funny
because it says h of xi on the
left,
but then on the right, there are
no xi's.
And that's because it is
returning the same prediction no
matter what input you give it.
Whether you leave at 6 AM, 8 AM,
9.30
AM, 11.45
PM,
the constant model returns the
same prediction.
And so then the question is,
what prediction should it
return?
What I've drawn for us here are
three different constants that
the constant model could
predict,
60,
70, and 100.
And the question we left off
Tuesday's lecture with was, is,
well, which constant should it
predict?
Where should we draw this
horizontal line?
And ultimately, everything we
are going to do today
is about answering that one
question.
Where should we draw that
horizontal line?
So if you ever get lost in the
weeds with the math, of which
there will be a lot today,
just come back to this picture.
Where do we draw the horizontal
line?
Now, what I've drawn on the page
or the screenshot that on this
page has three possible constant
models,
but there was like a templated
version of the constant model
that I stated on Tuesday.
What was the placeholder I used
on the right-hand side?
Yes, and remind me of your name?
I'm Alex.
Alex, right.
I think you used W.
W,
good.
And w,
what did I call a w on Tuesday?
Yes, remind me of your name?
Andrew.
I called it a parameter.
A parameter, good.
Parameters are aspects of our
model that we need to learn by
looking at the patterns in the
data.
So here,
we need to find a value of W
that makes sense for this
dataset.
If we had a different dataset,
well then our thinking behind
which W to use would be a little
different.
60, 70, 100 may not make sense.
What if I wanted a constant
model that predicted the year in
which people were born?
None of these values of W would
be good.
So it depends on the data.
Really quickly, just to
internalize the idea of a
parameter.
the other format of a model that
we considered on Tuesday was the
simple linear regression model.
And what did it look like?
What did it look like?
Yes, and remind me of your name.
You had W of 0 and then W of 1.
Good.
It says,
take in your xi and actually do
something with it.
What I mean by that is these
three don't look the same.
It seems like they change as x
changes.
And here,
remember, x is departure time.
And indeed,
what it returns is W0.
Typically, this is pronounced
W0, but sometimes I'll say W0 as
well.
plus w1 xi.
And this is just really a
rebranded y equals mx plus b.
It's not any more complicated
than that.
It's just that in machine
learning,
w is the term we use for,
or the variable we use for.
What are w0 and w1 here?
What would we call them?
Parameters.
Good, parameters.
So this simple linear regression
model has two parameters and
given a data set if we choose to
use the simple linear regression
model the question is well what
should we set these parameters
to so that the resulting model
fits the data well and what you
can see here is that some
choices of parameters do an okay
job like 160 for the intercept W
naught
and negative 10 for the slope W1
and some do an atrocious job,
like 20 and 5.
And so what we're trying to get
at is, well, how do we know
which combination of parameters
would do the best job?
Ideally, there's a way to do
this in a more principled
manner than just looking at the
page and eyeballing it.
Especially because we will soon
enter a territory where we have
more than one input variable or
more than one feature.
What if we have 10 features? So
I'm using 10 input variables to
predict how long my commute is
going to take.
Well, then,
I can't even draw the graph, at
least not natively, right?
Because I would need 10 axes to
represent my 10 input variables,
and then an 11th axis
to represent the actual commute
time.
So I would need to be able to
visualize in 11 dimensional
space.
But we're just humans, we can
only visualize in three
dimensional space, which is why
very quickly we will no longer
be able to directly visualize
the quantities we're working
with.
So we need to come up with
mathematical solutions that
don't rely on being able to see.
So we'll build intuition in two
dimensions and three dimensions,
and then come up with general
solutions that work beyond that.
So this is an overview of the
simple linear regression model,
but we're going to focus on the
constant model.
The goal for the rest of today
is how do we figure out what the
best constant is?
What is the best value of w?
All we're going to do for the
rest of the day,
what is the best value of w for
the constant model?
Sound good?
So what I want to do is turn
this into kind of like a game,
where for every value of w,
I give it a score.
For values of w that are very
far from my data,
like w equals 100 in the
furthest right option here,
it should have a really bad
score.
that indicates this is not a
good W.
And for values of W that are
closer to most of the data,
I should have good scores.
What's one way I could try and
come up with such a scoring
system?
And to illustrate,
let me actually simplify a
little and think of a smaller
data set.
of not the hundreds of commute
times in the scatter plot we
were just looking at,
but these five commute times.
And I should say y1 equals 72.
85 and y5 equals 92.
By the way, if you see me
looking over at my computer,
it's because I want to make sure
the numbers I write here are the
same as the ones that are in the
notes so that the examples all
are the same when you go back to
review.
OK, let's pretend we have this
example data set of just five
commute times.
Why did I just write y1 through
y5? Where are the x's here?
Where are the x's?
Paul.
It doesn't matter what they are
because it's not going to factor
into our thinking of what the
best constant to predict is
because the constant model
doesn't use x.
Okay and so goal
find the best
w in h of x i equals w.
Okay,
given this small example,
what is,
pretend I pick a value of w.
Let's say I pick w equals 80.
What's one way I could try and
measure how good or bad 80 is as
a value of W.
Yes, and remind me of your name?
Sam.
You could subtract each number
from 80.
Exactly.
The sort of initial thing we
might think of is just figure
out how far each of the data
points is from our prediction.
OK?
And indeed,
that's what we'll start with.
So let's pick
h of
xi equals 80.
Actually, before we get into the
specific example, So,
let me define what error would
be.
I should use orange for all of
my h of x i's because that's
what I use in the notes.
OK,
so this is the definition of
error,
yi minus h of xi.
All this is is just the fancy
way of saying actual minus
predicted.
The yi's are just these five
things for each value of i from
1 to 5 here.
I can compute this.
And the h of xi is what I'm
predicting.
And here, h of xi is just going
to be the same constant for all
values in my data set.
OK?
Let's test this out.
So then if I use h of xi equals
80,
what is the error for the first
data point?
y1.
Yeah, remind me of your name.
Ammar.
Good.
Minus a.
What about for the second data
point?
There,
I'd have y2 minus h of x2 equals
what,
Mar?
I'd have positive 10.
Let me do some highlighting
here.
But it seems like there's a
problem here.
What's the problem?
Remember, my ultimate goal here
is to think of a way to measure
the quality of a prediction in
which certain scores tell me a
prediction was bad and other
scores tell me a prediction was
good.
But what's kind of going on
here?
Sam?
It's going to be 2,
but it's really 18.
So it should be like,
you don't want it to be
negative.
Yeah, what we're getting at is
that it
doesn't seem like these scores
should be able to be negative,
OK?
What would the best possible
prediction be for, let's say,
y1?
If I wanted my prediction to be
as good as possible for y1,
what would the corresponding h
of x1 be?
Bella?
0.
The error would be 0, exactly.
And so h of x1 would be
72 for y1, because that's how we
would get the prediction
perfect.
And that would mean we would
have an error of 0.
That's as good as we could do.
What that tells us is values
closer to 0 should be better, or
smaller values should be better.
But negative 8 is technically
less than 10.
Yeah.
Actually,
that example didn't work the way
I wanted to.
But I think you see the point,
which is that these scores
shouldn't be negative.
Because if they could be
negative, and eventually what we
are going to try and do is come
up with one aggregated or total
score for the quality of the
prediction,
the positive scores and the
negative scores could cancel
out.
And what if I pick a prediction
that's really terrible,
like 61, for example?
What's the error for 61?
It's negative 19,
which is really bad, but it's
the smallest number that would
be on the screen, because
negative 19 is smaller than
negative 8 and positive 10.
So do we see the issue with
negative errors?
Good.
So what we want to do is come up
with a scoring system where
small values are consistently
good and big values are
consistently bad.
So we want to get rid of the
fact that some of these errors
are positive and some are
negative.
We want them to all be
non-negative.
So what are some remedies to
that situation?
Yeah,
the most natural thing to do
would be to just take the
absolute values of the errors.
So they just can't be negative.
The closer the actual was to
predicted,
the smaller the absolute error
would be.
The further away it is, the
larger the absolute error would
be.
That's a natural idea, but it's
actually not the idea we are
going to use,
at least not today.
We'll talk about that more on
Tuesday.
OK,
what are some other things we
could do?
Remind me of your name?
Emma.
You could square it.
Good.
There are plenty of other things
you could do too.
You could raise them to the
power of 4.
You could do e to the power of
these things, because e to the
power of something can't return
a negative number.
There's lots of possible things
you could do.
But squaring it turns out to be
the most convenient
mathematically.
And now you can maybe start to
see why we planted very specific
questions in yesterday's lab.
Okay if you remember yesterday's
lab worksheet there were
functions that involved
something minus something
squared and you had to take a
derivative.
Why is that?
Like why did we put that there?
Well it's because I knew we were
going to talk about squaring the
errors here and at some point
we're gonna have to take a
derivative.
And the kind of thing you should
be thinking about is, well,
our overall goal here is to find
the best w.
So somehow we are going to pose
this as a calculus question, and
derivatives are going to enter
the picture.
And what do you know about
absolute values?
What do you know about absolute
values?
Yes,
Andrew?
The derivatives are not
continuous.
Yeah, or the derivative isn't
defined everywhere.
Exactly, because the absolute
value curve looks like this.
And then at the point where
actual equals predicted, or
where the input to the absolute
value is zero, there's no
clearly defined derivative, so
it's a little harder to try and
use calculus to figure out the
best w there.
Which is why we are going to
start with squaring.
And when we square our error,
or take the absolute value,
what we've produced is called a
loss function.
A loss function measures
how wrong or how good or bad
a prediction is
for a single data point.
So the first loss function we
are going to see is called
squared loss.
Here's the formula for squared
loss.
The letter I will use to refer
to a loss function
is L with a subscript SQ,
standing for squared.
And it's going to take in two
inputs,
an actual y value,
yi,
and a predicted y value,
h of xi.
What's it going to return?
What do I write on the
right-hand side here?
Got it.
Would it be like yi minus h of x
of i squared?
Good.
It's just actual y value minus
predicted y value
squared.
So when you see this, all you
should think is actual minus
predicted squared.
What do you think the other or
next loss function we will learn
about is called?
Yeah.
Yeah, there's an absolute loss
as well.
Its formula, as you might
predict,
is still called L something, but
L abs takes in an actual y,
predicted y,
and returns the absolute value
of
the difference.
OK?
Like I said, we're going to
start with squared loss because
the squaring operation plays
nicely with calculus.
But we will come back to
absolute loss Maybe briefly at
the end of today's lecture, but
mostly on Tuesday.
Okay,
so now we have our like scoring
technique.
We know how we are going to
evaluate the quality of a
prediction
for all points in our data set.
So let's use squared loss.
There's a visual I want to bring
in here.
There we go.
What
I've done,
let me copy this as well.
This happens.
Okay.
There we go.
What I've done is drawn two
scatter plots.
The X positions of the five
points in each are irrelevant.
The Y positions are these five Y
values here.
Do we see that? Like this is at
72,
this is at 90,
this is at 61.
So it's the same data set that's
being visualized here.
And what I'm doing is I'm
visualizing
the squared loss for all five of
my data points
for two different choices of w.
Actually,
there's a step I skipped here
that could make this slightly
clearer.
What I've done here on this page
is I defined squared loss and
absolute loss for any hypothesis
function.
Age of xi could be super
complicated, involve squaring,
signs, whatever.
For the constant model,
the
formula simplifies.
So squared loss in general looks
like
actual minus predicted squared
but for the constant
model how does it simplify
yes
and remind me of your name Alex
it's just the actual minus W
good why I minus W squared
that's the simplification, and
that's because the constant
model just says h of xi is
equal to W.
I should have said that before.
And so now, are we clear on what
I mean by that?
The squared loss for each data
point is just this difference
between that y value and the W
that we're considering squared.
So now this plot makes a little
more sense because we are
considering two different
choices,
w,
right? And the squared loss that
we are looking at is yi minus w
squared.
On the left,
I've plotted out these squared
losses for w equals 85.
And on the right, I have w
equals 80.
And you can see that w equals 85
is better for some data points,
and w equals 80 is better for
others.
For example,
w equals 85 is really good
when y is equal to 85, because
there's no error,
and that's the squared loss is 0
as well.
Do we see that?
So the left one is good in some
cases, but it's also bad in some
cases.
Like this looks really bad.
Negative 24 squared, that's a
huge number,
576.
So the squared loss for that
data point is really bad.
And so maybe there's some way to
set this system up where it
encourages us not to pick 85,
because it seems like there's a
lot of loss here.
So keep that thought in mind.
The one on the right,
some of the numbers are bigger.
Some of the numbers are smaller.
And so the question is,
well,
given these five squared losses
for w equals 85 and separately
five squared losses for w equals
80,
how do we know which one is
better?
Because we're comparing five
different numbers here across
two different sets.
And what if we had a data set
with hundreds of points?
We're not just going to look at
100 squared losses
for every value of w we're
considering.
What could we do to make this
process a little simpler?
Yes, and remind me of your name?
My name's Chloe.
I'm going to sum up the error
with the ages greater.
Yeah, all we really need to do
is figure out which w had the
smaller total squared loss,
right?
And that's more or less what we
are going to do with one
Modification
Instead of total I'm gonna
compute the average but an
important point to make here is
that Now,
suppose w equals 80 has a
smaller total squared loss.
It also has a smaller average
squared loss,
right?
Why is that?
Yes? Same number of data points.
Exactly.
It's the same number of data
points in both cases,
right?
Pretend we have two classes at
the university.
Both have 50 students.
And class A's average height is,
I don't know, 5 foot 5.
Class B's average height is
5'8".
If you added up the heights of
everybody in Class A and Class
B,
Class B's is of course going to
be greater because they both
have 50 students.
But if the numbers of students
were different, then you
couldn't directly make that
comparison.
My point with that example is
that any time you are dealing
with situations with the same
number of data points,
comparing totals is the same as
comparing averages.
And I'm going to choose to
compare averages because
then the numbers don't get
super, super large when I have
lots of data points.
Pretend I have a million data
points and the total squared
loss may be some massive number.
But the average squared loss
doesn't need to be.
Okay, and it's more
interpretable in the scale of
the data, which is the kind of
thing we're going to explore in
just a little bit.
So the idea here is compute
the average
squared loss
for all w's we
are considering.
So here are our five data
points.
We'll say for w equals 85,
what does that look like?
What does my average squared
loss look like?
If I had to start writing this
out as an expression,
what would I write?
Paul.
Is it the summation of u minus
yi over
i?
Eventually, we will write this
in summation notation.
But for now, I want to keep the
variables out of it, and I just
want to write down some numbers
or figure out what numbers I
would like.
We don't need to do the actual
squaring, but I want to write
down a thing I could put in my
calculator.
72 minus 85 squared.
Good, exactly.
That's what I was getting at.
72 minus 85 squared plus 90
minus 85
squared plus dot dot dot plus 92
squared all over 5.
That's something I could put
into my calculator or tell me
one number.
If I do this for w equals 80,
I'd have a similar looking
expression.
The only difference is that
instead of 85s everywhere,
you'd see 80s.
Do we see how these are
essentially the same formula,
just 80s on the bottom and 85s
up top?
There's a mistake on the page.
Where's the mistake?
Very subtle.
Andrew.
That squared is in square
brackets.
Yeah, good.
OK,
so just to make sure we're on
the same page here, pretend I
plug this into the first
expression into a calculator.
I plug the second into the
calculator.
How does that tell me which w is
better?
Which w is better?
Whichever produces the lower
score.
Yeah,
we want the w with the lower
average squared loss.
OK.
So it seems like we have a
system where
if we think of values of w to
use,
we know how to give them a
score.
So if all 70 of us pick a w,
we could all compute the average
squared loss for this data set.
And then whichever one of us
picked the w with the lowest
average squared loss, that would
be the best among the things we
tried.
But again, ideally, we want to
think of a way of figuring out
the best w that doesn't involve
just randomly guessing possibly
good values.
So what I want to do is take
this calculation that's right
here and turn it into a function
where I can plug in any value of
w.
And that's how we're going to
start building to this
calculus-based approach that I
alluded to.
So let
me copy this data set again.
For any
w,
the average squared loss is
72 minus w squared
plus 90 minus w squared plus dot
dot dot
all the way through 92 minus w
squared all over 5.
Actually I'm going to write this
a little lower because I want to
give this a name.
Do you agree that this is a
function of just one variable,
The data points, the y's,
the setting in which we're
working assumes that those are
constant or they're not really
up for debate.
The data is what it is.
Our goal is to figure out what
the parameter should be.
So the data is not a variable
here, even though it is unknown
to us.
The only unknown here,
or the only variable here, is
what the value of w should be.
And so I'm intentionally writing
this as a function of
just w.
Now I've introduced a new symbol
here,
r.
R stands for empirical
risk,
which is just a fancy word
for average loss
for a whole data set.
Crucially though,
the letter L does not appear
here.
It would be wrong to put an L
where I've highlighted the R to
be.
Now if you take other machine
learning courses or read things
online,
sometimes they will call this
entire thing a loss function.
They'll say the average of these
squared errors is a loss
function.
But for this class, I want to
sort of maintain the distinction
that these individual pieces,
that's a loss function.
But the entire thing,
average of my losses, is a
different thing,
here called empirical risk,
which I will denote with the
letter R.
So now I have a function where I
can plug in values of w and see
which one leads me to the lowest
output.
And I want the value of w that
minimizes this function.
Now, this sounds a lot like
other problems that you've
solved before, or tried to solve
before, using calculus.
Do you agree?
OK.
And so what we're going to do
shortly
is figure out the general
solution.
But first,
I want us to guess.
Or actually,
before we even guess,
I want us to think about what
this looks like.
What does this graph look like?
The graph here, what does it
look like? Can you remind me of
your name again?
Brian.
It's a parabola.
Why?
It's the polynomial values,
um,
max,
it means new,
so.
Exactly.
If you look at all five of these
individual pieces,
72 minus w squared,
90 minus w squared, and so on,
each one of those is a
quadratic, or it's a parabola,
if the axes were w and the
output.
Now,
when you look at this more
complicated expression, it seems
like it may be more complicated
than a parabola, but it's not.
And if you expanded out the
numerator, which there's no need
to,
but if you did, you would still
see that it's something times w
squared plus something times w
plus something, which is just a
parabola.
What this means is that what we
are looking at here
is a graph of this form.
w is on this axis, and the
output average squared loss for
our chosen w is on the y-axis.
Why do I know it looks like this
and doesn't point downwards?
Caleb, right?
Yeah, everything's squared.
Yeah, because all of these terms
are being squared, which means
they couldn't be negative,
which means this parabola can't
extend infinitely negative.
And if we think about
conceptually how we set this up,
it seems like there would be a
possible best prediction, but no
possible worst prediction.
If you think of a bad
prediction,
you can make it even worse by
moving a little further away
from the data.
If a million is bad,
a million and one is even worse.
It would have an even higher
average square root.
So there's no maximum,
but there is a minimum.
Because we know these things
can't be negative, so this
couldn't point infinitely
downwards.
So this is what it's going to
look like.
And the question is,
what is the input
that gets us to this vertex?
And we know what the answer is
going to be from yesterday's
lab, because this is essentially
the same formula,
just you didn't have all of this
context going into the lab.
What is the answer going to end
up being?
Maaj?
The mean?
Yeah, the mean or the average of
the data points.
And we're going to prove that
once and for all,
not just with this example of
five data points, but for any
arbitrary data set.
Okay?
That's what we're about to do.
Before we do that,
what questions do we have so far
with anything that we've done
today?
What questions do we have?
So we talked about, before we
talked about risk,
we talked about error.
Is error just the expected minus
the predicted?
Actual minus the predicted,
yeah.
So these individual pieces
without the square,
like 72 minus 80 and 90 minus
80,
we would call those things
errors.
But when you square them, then
that's squared loss,
or just the loss.
Yes,
and remind me of your name?
Alex.
Alex, right.
Why couldn't you just take,
I don't like you're sort of like
dividing it by like the total
number of them, because you're
trying to find the average.
But like why couldn't you just
like minimize as sort of just
the summation of the loss
functions.
Like, why do we need to divide
by 5? We don't.
We would get the same result if
we didn't divide by 5.
OK?
What I'm saying, though, is that
as a principle for the rest of
the semester,
whenever we're dealing with loss
functions,
the convention we will use is to
average them rather than sum
them just because it keeps the
numbers smaller and more
interpretable.
Imagine we had a million data
points.
The average of a million squared
losses doesn't have to be that
big, but the total of a million
squared losses would be pretty
big.
So it makes it a little easier
to compare
average squared losses across
different situations.
So we know this is the graph
that we are minimizing.
And by the way, actually, I
should say,
what we are about to do is set
this up and find a formula for
the minimizing w that is the
best w,
the one that makes the best
predictions.
We're going to do that using
calculus, But there are other
ways you could do it.
Like when you were in high
school, you learned how to find
the vertex of a parabola and you
didn't know about calculus,
right?
There are things like completing
the square and various other
things and so in homework one
There's a question where we have
you do that.
We give you the formula for
average squared loss and we say
hey
Using these algebraic techniques
figure out what the best W
should be
Assuming you don't know how to
do calculus and we walk you
through a different way You
could do it.
So calculus is one way, but it's
not the only way to arrive here
What I want to do though is come
up with a general formula
for average squared
loss
for the constant model.
Everything we're discussing here
is specific to the constant
model.
We made our calculation of
squared loss simpler by saying h
of xi equals w.
If h of xi equals some more
complicated thing,
but all of this would become
more complicated as well.
But we're sticking with the
constant model for now.
So suppose we have n
data points
y1, y2,
dot dot dot through yn.
n is the usual place holder we
will use in this class for an
unknown number of data points
and you will see this every day
for the rest of the semester.
The average squared loss
of the constant model,
That's an orange.
h of xi equals w
is
going to use that same symbol
from before,
R.
First, I want to write this
without summation notation.
Can someone help me out here?
If I had to write this out,
what is a general formula for
average squared loss?
Andrew?
y1 minus w squared,
and then ellipses plus n minus w
squared.
Good.
I want the squared loss for my
first data point.
And you said overhead, right?
Perfect.
I want the squared loss for my
first data point which again is
actual y-value minus predicted
y-value which is just W here
squared plus the second actual
y-value minus
predicted y-value squared plus
all the way
through the last y-value minus
the
predicted y-value squared.
And what I divide all of the spy
is the number of data points.
Good.
Now, this formula looks a little
more confusing than the one we
saw a few slides ago, because
there are way more symbols in
it.
The previous formula only had a
w and then had numbers like 72,
90,
61.
This is the same formula,
though.
It just has placeholders for
what the data would be.
n is just the number of data
points,
and the yi's are placeholders
for what the data are.
But the setting is the same in
that And we don't have control
over what the y's are.
They're just given to us by our
data set.
We collect data, and they're
given to us.
The thing we have control over
is what w we pick to make the
predictions with.
So that's why this is still
written as a function of just
the w's, and the y's are given.
If I wanted to write this using
summation notation,
how could I do that?
This is why we had some practice
with summation notation
yesterday.
Yeah.
You do 1 over n,
and then the summation will go
from i equals 1 to n.
Good.
And inside the summation you
have y sub i minus w squared.
Awesome.
You can see that the factor of 1
over n is the same in both.
It's just written a little
differently, but it doesn't have
to be like I could have not had
a 1 over n there and I could
have just put all of this over
n, it would be the same formula.
And what this is saying is first
plug in i equals 1,
whatever that is, add it to my
total.
Then plug in i equals 2,
whatever that is,
add it to my total.
And keeps adding this up sort of
like a four loop.
If it helps you anytime you see
a summation,
just think of someone saying
total equals 0 before it.
And then for i in range,
whatever these indices are,
add this quantity.
The difference,
like what is the one difference
between how the indices work in
summation notation and how they
work in programming four loops?
There's a subtle difference.
For summation,
it's inclusive? Yeah,
it includes both i equals 1 and
i equals n.
OK?
Whereas in a for loop, this
would not include n,
right?
All right, so are we comfortable
with this formula
for average squared loss
for the constant model?
OK,
so now our goal is to just find
the w that makes this function
output the smallest possible
number.
And how we are going to do that,
as I implied earlier, is by
taking its derivative and
setting it equal to 0.
That's the approach we will use
at least today.
All right,
so I'll say goal.
Find the w that minimizes
average squared loss.
How?
Take derivative
equal
to 0.
Why are we doing that again? Why
do I want the w that minimizes
this function? What was the
point of all of this, again?
Brian?
The middle is finding the w
value.
That fits like the data.
Exactly.
I want to just keep reiterating
that so that we don't get lost
in the weeds here.
The point of all of this is to
just figure out what w best
makes predictions.
Again, all we are trying to do
is find the optimal place to
draw this horizontal line.
And if we take the derivative of
average squared loss and set it
equal to zero,
what it should tell us is where
to place that horizontal line in
order for the predictions to be
as good as they can be on the
data that we've collected.
Do we agree?
Okay, so that's the point of all
of this.
Now, we've been calling this
function
average squared loss.
There's another more common term
for this that you'll see a lot
in machine learning, which is
why this more common term is
what we will call this from now
on, but it's the same thing.
it's mean squared error
and sometimes this is
abbreviated MSE
so this is the more common term
for the formula that's at the
top of the page here but it's
referring to the same idea and
it's really the same three words
just slightly different right we
have mean and average the
squared is the It's the same.
Loss, that was nice because it
symbolizes that this is not just
actual minus predicted, but it's
some function of that.
It's squared, and we will still
call the loss function a loss
function.
Here, you sort of have to look
at the squared error
as one term, saying the errors
have been squared.
So mean squared error, or MSE,
is the more common way of
referring to average squared
loss, but it's the same concept.
I just want to have this written
down here, And this is written
in the notes as well,
just so that when you see this
here and in other contexts, you
know that these are all
referring to the same thing.
Which is why if you look at the
section in chapter 1.2
of the notes that we're at, it's
called minimizing mean squared
error, not minimizing average
squared loss.
Same thing,
though.
OK?
OK with terminology,
anyone curious or sort of have
questions about what any of the
various words we've introduced
today mean?
Because I know there have been a
lot.
Yes, Allison.
What was your definition for
empirical risk?
Good.
That's just another word for
these things.
But empirical risk is a little
more general because it is not
specific to any one loss
function.
Like, if we were using absolute
loss,
we could also call that
empirical risk.
But I was planning on writing
down sort of a formal definition
of empirical risk when we come
back on Tuesday when we compare
the choice of squared loss to
other possible loss functions.
For now, we'll focus on just
squared loss.
So does R sub SQ mean the
empirical risk using the
squared? Exactly.
Exactly, using the squared loss.
Yeah,
good.
So if we were using absolute
loss, that would be a subscript
abs.
And the kind of question you
will start to see in homework,
not homework one, but homework
two,
is we will cook up some other
loss function that you haven't
seen before and say,
find the parameters that make
the best predictions if we're
using this loss function.
And you'll see lots of questions
like that next week's lab,
next week's homework.
That's the kind of thing we will
study.
But I'm starting with squared
loss because it's the most
common choice and a natural
first choice.
So everyone's on the same page.
We have established what the
point of minimizing this
function is.
Again, it all comes back to
making the best predictions that
we can.
Comfortable with that?
We have about 20 minutes
remaining, but I will commit to
my promise of still taking a
little bit of a break,
even though that should have
come earlier.
Why don't we write that there.
Make sure to check in for
attendance.
We'll do that now.
Feel free to go to the bathroom
really quick if you need to.
We'll take a maybe three or four
minute break.
and let me open the attendance
poll so you can check in.
Give me another minute or two.
Stretch your legs and then final
stretch.
Time for the calculus.
We'll get started in another
minute.
try it in a different browser.
It'll ask for a location just
once but it won't Do
you
have
a different browser if you have
Chrome on your phone?
If that doesn't work then I can
check you in manually after.
Okay,
has everyone checked in or is
anyone still working on it?
Okay, come up to me afterwards
and I'll write down your name
and make sure you get the
credit.
Everyone else OK? Checked in,
got your questions in,
good.
All right.
So remember,
make sure this thing's on.
Our goal is to find the w that
minimizes this function.
This function overall, we call
it average squared loss.
The new name for it is mean
squared error.
And the goal is to find the w
that makes it output the
smallest possible number.
And that w will be the magical w
that makes the best predictions
What we said we would do is take
the derivative of it with
respect to w
So let's try and do that
now as an aside as a side quest
what I want to do is maybe go to
a different slide and
Take the derivative of this
thing with respect to w
The reason I want to do this
individual derivative separately
is that once we have this, we
can use it to more easily find
the overall derivative.
So what's the derivative of yi
minus w squared
with respect to w?
What is it? Alex.
It would be negative 2 yi minus
1.
Good.
And how did you get there?
I'm going to use a chain rule.
Good.
So remember, the chain rule, the
way that I like thinking about
it,
is that the derivative of some
complicated expression
with respect to w,
maybe we'll say the derivative
of box to the power of n
with respect to w, is equal to n
times box to the n minus 1
times the derivative of what's
in the box directly.
So here, that's how you'd use
the chain rule along with the
power rule.
Do we agree?
That applied here,
the n,
no, this is not n, the number of
data points.
Maybe I should have used a
different variable, but this is
the rule you would have seen and
calculus would have used then.
That applied here gives us 2
times yi minus w to the power of
1, times the derivative of just
yi minus w.
So I have 2 times yi minus w,
and what is this piece?
Just 1.
Not 1.
Negative 1.
Good.
Because the coefficient on w is
negative 1,
and this is sort of the tricky
thing.
The yi is a constant from the
perspective of w,
right? changing w does not
change the yi.
So we multiply that by negative
1.
And so we can collect out the
constants up front.
So we have negative 2yi minus w.
Note that since we are squaring
our loss,
I like doing actual minus
predicted.
But you could do predicted minus
actual squared.
And you'd have the same thing.
And this would be w minus yi
squared.
And the derivative would be 2
times w minus yi.
There wouldn't be the negative
in front, but I just like actual
minus predicted,
so that's what we'll use.
OK.
Why did I find this derivative
separately?
How is that going to help me
here?
What does that help with?
Yeah, Kevin? Because when you're
doing a summation,
you can treat the derivative to
the inside and it's the whole
thing.
Exactly.
Remember, one of the key rules
you learned in calc 1 is that if
you have two functions being
added together,
the derivative of the overall
sum is equal to the sum of their
derivatives added up.
So if you have f of x plus g of
x,
that entire thing's derivative
is the derivative of f of x plus
the derivative of g of x, which
is why all I really need to do
here
to apply the derivative
operation to the sum is just
have a new sum made up of the
sum of the derivatives.
OK.
And then what do I do about our
1 over n friend up here?
What do we do with that?
It just stays there.
It stays there.
It's a constant with respect to
w.
So they can stay there.
We're going to move into the
sum.
and now what I'm going to
replace
yi minus w with
is the derivative with respect
to w of yi minus w squared
that is the thing we found on
the previous page it's negative
2 yi minus w and collecting
like how can I Let's try this
further, actually.
Let's ask that.
You can pull the negative 2 out
outside of the summation.
Good, the negative 2 is just a
constant being multiplied by
every term in the sum.
That's the same as just doing
the sum without the negative 2
and multiplying the result
afterwards by negative 2, which
is why I can pull the constant
up front.
And that gives me negative 2
over n times the sum
of yi minus w.
So this is the derivative,
OK?
Perhaps looks different than the
derivatives you're used to
calculating in calc 1, because
those probably didn't have
summations in them.
But this is the type of
derivative we will see a lot in
this class,
OK?
OK, we got that.
What's next?
Yeah?
Is that a 0? Yeah, all we need
to do now is set this derivative
equal to zero.
So let's write that one more
time.
And now we're just going to set
this equal to zero and solve.
So, let's copy this.
What's the first thing we can
do?
It's all for W, to be clear.
What's the first thing we can do
to make that process a little
simpler?
Yeah.
And remind us of your name?
Chinmay.
Chinmay, right.
Yeah, the negative 2 over N, we
can get rid of it.
Why?
Awesome.
Because if you multiply n by 0,
that's 0.
And then divide by 2,
Exactly.
We could multiply by negative n
over 2,
which is sort of what you'd have
to multiply negative 2 over n by
to get 1 to get rid of the
constant.
And on the right side, 0 times
negative n over 2 would still be
0.
So it's just a way to free up
some space and make the
expression a little clearer on
the left-hand side.
So I'll say multiply both sides
by negative n over 2.
Now, where did this over n come
from in the first place?
Like, why is it there?
Alex?
Because we're taking the
average.
We divide it all by the number
of days.
Yeah, it's because we are
computing average squared loss
or mean squared error.
If we instead did the sum of
squared losses,
we just wouldn't have the over
n.
But this calculation for finding
the best w would be the same,
because the over n dropped out
of our
formula either way.
So average squared loss or total
squared loss,
the math ends up being the same
at this stage.
By the way, how many people
here's name is Alex? I think
there are at least three people
here.
Yeah, OK, there are three
people.
OK,
that was confusing me a little,
But OK.
Anyways, back to this.
What we're trying to do now is
isolate for w.
How can we do that?
How can we isolate for w?
Ammar?
Just distribute the summation.
Awesome.
I'll get to you next.
I keep looking this way when I'm
asking for questions.
Yeah.
So how do I distribute the
summation? You can just split
up,
so the sum of y1 minus the sum
of w.
Good.
Whenever you have a summation,
and the thing being summed
itself has an addition or
subtraction, you can distribute
the sum operator across that.
What that looks like here is
something like,
let me free up some space here.
Maybe I think this part was
clear.
This is the sum of yi's minus
the
sum of w's.
How do I make this simpler?
How do I make this simpler? Yes,
it reminds me of your name
again?
Gustavo.
So the w sum term, wouldn't it
just be n times w? Good, why?
Because you're just summing w n
times.
That's just like w plus w plus w
would be just n times w.
Exactly.
All this is doing is n times,
it's adding the value of w.
There's no subscript i here, so
the sum isn't any more
complicated than that.
It's the sum of a constant n
times, so this is just n times
w.
And so simplifying that gives us
the sum of yi's minus nw equals
zero.
And now we're more or less done
because our goal was to isolate
for w.
On the left we have the sum of
yi's and on the right we have n
times w.
Now, finally, what do I need to
do to isolate for w?
Divide by n.
Yeah, I divide both sides by n,
and I'll reverse the order here
just so it's a little more
natural.
What this gives me is a formula
for what?
It's not the mean.
Yeah, it's the mean, or the
average, of the y's.
And now I'm going to put a star
on this w because we've found
that it is the best one,
or it is the optimal w.
And this is just,
indeed,
the average slash mean of
the y's.
And I think that's a pretty cool
result, because you already knew
about the concept of an average
and a mean before this class.
But now you know a little more
about it, which is that if your
goal is to make a constant
prediction for all future data
points based
on some collection of numbers,
the mean of the data is actually
the best constant prediction you
can make.
It's not just convenient, but
it's also the best.
But it's the best under a very
specific lens, which is the lens
in which you measure the quality
of predictions using squared
loss.
If we instead picked another way
to measure how good or bad a
prediction is,
the mean doesn't necessarily end
up still being the best.
If we think of a different loss
function and a different way of
quantifying how good or bad
predictions are,
we may end up with a different
best W.
Okay, so to recap,
this function,
1 over n times the sum of
yi minus w squared,
which went by many names, mean
squared error, average squared
loss, both of those are also
called empirical risk,
that function is minimized at
w star equals
the mean of of the
y's.
The star means w star is an
optimal parameter.
It's the star because it's
special.
And so all of this was set up
really to be able to come back
to this plot and say,
well, now I actually know what
the best W to choose is.
I know what the best horizontal
position
to use for my constant
predictions is.
It's the average of all of the y
values in my data set.
Do we agree with that?
You can't do any better if your
goal
or if your sort of measuring
stick for what makes a good
prediction is one that has low
average squared loss.
If you think of a different
scoring system, well then maybe
a different constant prediction
would end up being the best.
To give you a preview of what's
to come on Tuesday,
let's see if you can predict,
I guess no pun intended,
what would happen if we used a
different loss function.
If we used absolute loss
instead,
the best prediction isn't the
mean.
But what is it, if you have to
guess?
It's not the mean.
It's the median,
yeah.
We will work through why that's
the case on Tuesday and you
should read a little bit of
chapter 1.3
to start to see why that's the
case.
But my point is that the mean is
the best constant prediction.
That's a nice one-sentence
summary, but it's assuming we
use squared loss as our loss
function.
Okay,
now to get us thinking about
what it would look like if we
used other loss functions, But
what I want to write
down, and this is what we will
start with on Tuesday,
is what I call the three-step
modeling recipe,
which summarizes everything
we've done
and shows us how we could repeat
these steps,
but with maybe different models
and different loss functions.
The three steps we followed
today We're to choose a model,
choose a loss function.
Let me move this up a little.
And the third thing we did was
we minimized
average loss
to find optimal
parameters.
Why?
Because that'll make the best
predictions.
What is the model we chose
today?
We called it the constant model.
h of xi equals w.
Make that H a little cleaner.
What is the loss function we
chose today?
Squared loss.
What did the average of this
loss function look like across
an entire data set?
Well,
to get that,
all I did is I plugged in h of
xi equals w, which is my
specific model that I want to
use here for h of xi here.
That's how I made the
calculations a little simpler.
That's why only a w appears
here.
And what this looked like was 1
over n times the sum
where i goes from 1 to n for my
n data points,
of yi minus w squared.
And through calculus, we found
that the best w is the mean
of the yi's.
This is the process, really,
that we followed in today's
lecture.
But it's also the process, more
or less, that is used for
training all supervised learning
models.
So including super complicated
neural networks that predicts
where there are cavities in your
teeth, so the Dyson camera
sprays it or whatever,
they use the same process.
They just have a larger data set
and a more complicated model,
but ultimately it's the same
thing.
They choose a model,
they choose a loss function, and
then somehow minimize average
loss to find optimal parameters.
Now one thing I'll say, to make
that connection a little
clearer,
is here average loss
was a function of just one input
variable, because we only had
one parameter.
The only thing we had to decide
once we picked that we were
using the constant model is
where should we draw the
constant.
But next week we will upgrade to
a model that has two parameters,
the simple linear regression
model.
And then this average loss for
that will get even more
complicated and we will have to
look at multivariate calculus
techniques.
If you think about the Dyson AI
toothbrush thing,
that model has millions or
billions of parameters.
Okay, so there isn't a closed
form formula that they can use
that just says,
okay, here are the best
parameters to use, which is why
you have to estimate the best
parameters
using programming techniques,
which we will cover later in the
class.
That's what gradient descent is.
But the final thing I wanted to
say is that like one of the
companies you hear about a lot,
NVIDIA right now, you know, it's
worth trillions of dollars.
The reason they're worth
trillions of dollars is really
just because of this third step.
is because all of these
companies are using their GPUs
to efficiently find optimal
model parameters to make
whatever predictions their model
is designed for.
So really, this three-step
process is what underpins all of
these modern advancements that
you're hearing about.
And we will come back to this on
Tuesday.
I have office hours right after
this as well if you want to chat
or ask about homework or
anything else.
They're in my office, which is
on the fourth floor.
The water picked too fresh to
bite.
It gets you sick.
You need to make sure you get
the insulin.
I like how much she matches the
protein.
Can you read the report to me?
So when you say like 20 seconds,
it's more 20 seconds.
Alright.
Thank you so much.
That's what, the math is almost
to the best teacher.
Yeah.
Your professor was doing the
math.
W will end up being the B.
And if you didn't get your
attendance credit, just let me
know and I'll, uh, he almost
crashed.
What?
Yeah, that's okay.
I don't have another class.
Remind me of your name.
Okay,
trick.
Cool.
Stop them.
Perfect.
And that was fun.
I think it was fun.
Check.
Okay.
Let me ask you a question.
Why don't you come upstairs and
take a look at the table?
Max.
I mean,
take a look at the table.
I don't think I actually did too
much.
No, I wish I could.
I think I should.
Hold on a second.
Yeah.
Yeah, I know you should take a
look at the table.
We have a smaller baby.
They had those at best of all.
No, I just happened to have a
Coke at my house.
What's that all about?
I don't know.
I went to do the appendix and
said I wasn't at the
destination.
location, if that happens a lot,
I just grab her to the class
away,
and that's it.
Hi.
Wait, were you done asking
things? I'm gonna ask after.
Oh, okay.
If I were to follow you.
Okay.
I'll double check for you.
Yeah,
thanks for letting me know.
Oh, yeah, I heard it once.
Yeah,
I gotta think of another
solution, because the way that
it gives me the attendance also
doesn't have people's emails, it
just has their name, which is
harder to cross-reference with
the roster,
so I do something different.
The idea would be I just
memorize everyone's name and I
just put it down in here.
I mean, that'd be a lot for you.
They have one right now, I'm
sure other classes have
attendance,
like online attendance networks.
I mean,
the easier way to do it would be
with a Google forum.
I wanted to try this because it
tries to make sure that you're
here,
and I want white people
protecting you.
Yeah
We'll see you in the next video.